嘿，你们好
hey, what's up guys
我是Cherno，欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
my name is Cherno, welcome back to my OpenGL series
今天，我们将讨论的，都是关于着色器的
today, we're going to be talking all about shaders
最后，我们终于可以在屏幕上看到一些东西了
finally, and we're finally going to be able to actually see something on the screen
那么，上一次，我们讲了顶点属性
so, last time, we talked about vertex attributes
并且在那之前，我们讨论过需要缓冲区的顶点对象之类的东西
and before that, we talked about vertex objects that takes buffers and all that stuff
所以如果你还没看过，一定要看看这些视频
so definitely check out those videos if you haven't
只需要点击上面的链接
by just clicking on the link up there
并且经过上一集，你们中的一些人已经能够在屏幕上看到一些东西了
and from last episode, some of you were actually able to already see something on the screen
那么，如果我们深入研究上次的代码
and if we dive into the code that we were at last time
在这里，我们只是写了这两行代码
over here, we basically just throw these two lines
如果我尝试在没有任何着色器之类的情况下运行这个应用程序
if I try and run this application as is without any kind of shader stuff at all
然后你会在我的电脑上看到
then you'll see on my computer
它真的运行起来了
it actually works
并且我们确实在正确的顶点位置看到了一个三角形或者白色三角形
and we do seem to see a triangle or white triangle at our correct vertex positions
这实际上就是我们在这里指定的
which we actually specified over here
所以为什么会这样呢
so how come that's happening
答案就是
and the answer to that is that
一些显卡驱动实际上会为你提供一个默认的着色器
some GPU drivers will actually provide you with a default shader
在你实际上没有提供自己的着色器的时候
if you haven't actually provided your own shader
并且这似乎就是这里正在发生的事情
and that was that's what seems to be happening here
但这确实是基于你现在的驱动
but this is something that is really based on your drivers
现在，我只是在这台真正的笔记本上用Intel显卡驱动运行这个
right now, I'm just running this with the Intel drivers on this actual laptop
不过我也有一个NVIDIA的显卡
however I do also have an NVIDIA GPU
这可能需要在以后为了更重要的事情不得不切换吧
which will probably have to switch too later for more serious things
但话虽如此
but that being said
它完全依赖于驱动
it's completely driver dependent
所以我真的不想，这就是为什么我上次没有运行它
so, I don't really want to kind of, that's why I didn't run it last time
并且我也不想鼓励你这么做
and I don't really want to encourage that
因为它可能最终会，只有你们中的一些人能运行
because it'll probably end up working for some of you
但不是对于你们所有人
but not for all of you
然后你们中的一些人会觉得我的代码不能运行
and then some of you will be like my code doesn't work
这不是真的意味着
it's not really meant to
OpenGL标准中并没有说
there's nothing in the OpenGL standard that actually says
如果你写了我们做的代码，你应该会看到一个三角形
you should see a triangle if you write the code that we've done
现在，这实际上只是取决于显卡制造商，他们说
right now, that's actually just up to the GPU manufacturers to say
嘿，你知道吗
hey, you know what
如果你不提供一个着色器
if you don't provide a shader
我们将为你只写一个基本的着色器
we'll just write a basic one for you
这样你至少可以更容易地调试你的代码，或之类的事情
so that you can at least debug your code a bit easier, or something like that
今天，我们实际上要写我们自己的着色器
today, we're actually going to write our own shaders
所以，每个人脑海里的第一个问题是
so, the first question on everyone's mind is
什么是着色器
what is a shader
一个着色器基本上就是一个运行在你的显卡上的一个程序(代码)
a shader is basically just a program that runs on your GPU
这是你应该能想到的一切
that's all you should be thinking of
当你想到一个着色器的时候
when you think about a shader
至于程序，我的意思是，就像一段代码
by program, I just mean, like a block of code
它是我们可以在计算机上以文本或字符串形式编写的代码
it's code that we can write as text as a string on our actual computer
然后我们可以把它给OpenGL
then we can give it to OpenGL
我们可以把它发到显卡上
we can send it to the graphics card
像其他程序一样编译它，像其他程序一样链接它
compile it like any other program, and link it like any other program
然后像运行其他程序一样运行它，但是
and then run it like any other program, but
不同的是，它实际上是在我们的显卡上运行的
the difference is that it actually is run on our GPU on our graphics card
而不是像这个c++程序那样在我们的CPU上
and not on our CPU like this c++ program is
那么为什么我们需要程序完全在显卡上运行
so why do we need programs to actually run on the GPU at all
为什么我们必须编写代码，然后在显卡上运行
why do we have to write code and then run it on the GPU
好吧
well
显然，我们正在学习图形编程
obviously we're learning about graphics programming
因此，显卡在这方面发挥了重要作用
so, the graphics card does play a major role in that
但具体来说
but specifically the reason
我们想要能够为显卡编程是因为
that we want to be able to program the GPU is because
我们希望能够告诉显卡该做什么
well, we want to be able to tell the GPU what to do
我们想要利用显卡的能力在屏幕上绘制图形
we want to utilize the power of the GPU to actually draw graphics on the screen
这并不意味着我们所做的一切
now that doesn't mean that everything we do
我们都得在显卡上做
we need to do on the GPU
或者我们应该以着色器的形式使用显卡
or we should be going on the GPU in the form of a shader
但CPU在某些方面还是更快
there are some things that the CPU is still faster at
并且随着这个系列的深入
and as we kind of progress through this series
我们可能会发现一些我们更喜欢在CPU上做的事情
we'll probably find some things that we will prefer to do on the CPU
然后可能只是将结果数据发送给显卡
and then maybe just send the result the resulting data to the GPU
同时仍然在CPU上进行处理
while still doing that, processing on the CPU
但话虽如此
but that being said
有些事情是不可否认的
there are undeniably things
很多事情都与图形有关
a lot of things to do with graphics
显卡的速度要快得多
that the GPU is simply going to be way faster at
那么这就是着色器派上用场的地方
and that's where shader has come in handy
不仅仅是在我们想遵从的时候
now not just when we want to defer things
现在不仅仅是当我们想要
now, not just when we want to kind of
把东西从CPU上拿出来放到显卡上
take things from the CPU and put them on the GPU
但从根本上
but fundamentally
我们得给显卡编程
we need to be able to program the GPU
因为
because
即使是在画这个简单三角形的时候
even in the form of drawing of drawing this really simple triangle
我还是需要能够告诉显卡
I still want to be able to tell the GPU
如何画这个三角形
how to draw that triangle
对吧，就像，顶点位置该在哪儿
right, like, where did the vertex positions go
三角形应该是什么颜色的
what color should the triangle be
应该怎么画
how should it be drawn
诸如此类的东西，对吧
all that kind of stuff, right
当我们进入更复杂的三维场景时
when we actually get into more complex 3D scenes, as well
光源就是一个很好的例子
lighting is a great example of
为什么我们想要为显卡编程
why we want to be able to program the GPU
光源是如何运行的，诸如此类的东西
how does lighting work, all of that stuff
我不想做得太早
I don't want to get too ahead of myself
但所有这些在某种程度上都需要被编程
but all of that stuff needs to be program somehow
显卡不知道怎么做，对吧
the GPU doesn't just know, how to do this, right
我们需要告诉显卡
we need to tell the GPU
如何处理我们发送的数据
what to do with the data that we've sent it
这就是着色器的本质
and that is what a shader fundamentally is
在这一集里
now in this episode
以及对于大多数(学习)OpenGL
and for most of OpenGL
并且对于大多数图形编程
and for most of graphics programming
我们和你可能都会把重点放在
we're and you as well probably going to be focused on
两种着色器
two types of shaders
就是，顶点着色器和片段着色器
vertex shaders and fragment shaders
顺便说一下, 片段着色器也被称为像素着色器
fragment shaders are also known as pixel shaders, by the way
到目前为止，这两种着色器类型是
so these two shader types are by far
最受欢迎的两种，并且
the two kind of most popular ones, and
可能你90%的时间都会用到它们
probably the ones that you will be using 90% of the time
还有其他的着色器类型，细分曲面着色器
there are other shader types, tessellation shaders
几何着色器
geometry shaders
计算着色器之类的东西，如果你在做
that kind of stuff compute shaders, if you're doing like
完全是所有的东西，
completely kind of all the stuff as well
那儿有许多不同类型的着色器
there are many different types of shaders
不要认为只有顶点和片段着色器
don't think that there are just vertex and fragment shaders
就这样，你做完了这儿所有的着色器，还有更多
that's it, you're done that's all there is, there's much more
它们确实会派上用场
and they do come in handy
当你开始接触更高级的东西时
when you kind of start getting to the more advanced stuff
在本系列中，我们肯定会进一步介绍这些类型的着色器
and we will certainly be covering those types of shader further down, in this series
当我们讲到更复杂的图形时
when we get to more complex graphics
但是现在对于90%的着色器编程来说
but for now and for like 90% of shader programming
你可能会处理顶点和片段或像素着色器
you're probably going to be dealing with vertex and fragment or pixel shaders
就是这样，首先，我们来谈谈这到底意味着什么
that's it, so first of all, let's talk about what that actually means
什么是顶点着色器，什么是片段着色器
what does a vertex shader, what is a fragment shader
它们是什么
what are they
为什么是这两种类型
why they're two types
我们如何使用它们
how do we use them
所以，我知道，我还没真正讲过OpenGL管道
so I know, I haven't really covered the OpenGL pipeline
或者只是标准的图形渲染管道
or the just standard kind of graphics rendering pipeline yet
但它大致是如何工作的
but how does roughly works
所以你们应该在脑子里想象一下
so really the picture that, you should be having in your head
我们在CPU上写了一堆数据
is that we've written a bunch of data on the CPU
我们已经向显卡发送了一些数据
we've sent some data to the GPU
我们已经发出了一个叫做DrawCall指令的东西
we've issued something called a DrawCall
在发出DrawCall指令之前，我们也绑定了某些状态
we've bound certain states as well before issuing that DrawCall
最后我们进入了着色器的阶段
and finally we kind of get to the shader stage of things
或者说是显卡
or rather the GPU gets to
实际处理DrawCall指令并在屏幕上绘制一些东西
actually processing the DrawCall and drawing something on the screen
并且我们在屏幕上看到了一个三角形
and we get to see a triangle on the screen
这个特定的过程基本上就是渲染管道，对吧
that specific process is basically the rendering pipeline, right
我们如何在屏幕上从有数据到有结果的
how do we go from having data to actually having a result on our screen
现在，当显卡开始绘制三角形时，着色器就派上用场了
now, shader come in handy, when the GPU actually starts drawing its triangle
顶点着色器和片段着色器是顺着管道的两种不同的着色器类型
and vertex and fragment shaders are two different shader types that are along that pipeline
所以当我们真正发出DrawCall指令时
so when we actually issue a DrawCall
顶点着色器会被调用
what happens is the vertex shader will get called
然后片段着色器会被调用
and then the fragment shader will get called
然后我们会在屏幕上看到结果
and then we'll see a result on the screen
在这两者之间有很多东西，我已经跳过了
now there are many things in between that, I have skipped over
为了简单起见
for simplicity's sake
在顶点着色器调用之前有很多阶段
there are many stages before the vertex shader
在调用顶点和片段着色器之间有许多阶段
many stages in between the vertex and fragment shader
以及在片段着色器和光栅化阶段之间也有也多阶段
as well as between the fragment shader and the rasterization stage
诸如此类的东西
and all that stuff
我现在不太想讲这个
I don't want to really cover that right now
我尽量简单点说
I'm trying to give this simple
所以只记住这一点
so just keep that in mind
你们这些高级人才都知道到底发生了什么
all of you advanced people who know exactly what's going on
但还是为了一些原因坚持在看这些视频
but it's still watching these videos for some reason
顺便说一下，我是在开玩笑
I'm kidding by the way
几乎每个人都应该看看这些视频
pretty much everyone should watch these videos
因为它可能会让你觉得你错过了很多细节
because it might feel in a lot of gaps that you're missing
但无论如何，重点是
but anyway the point being
我在简化这个
I am simplifying this
所以我们从
so we go from
DrawCall指令
the DrawCall
到顶点着色器，再到片段着色器
to the vertex shader, to the fragment shader,
最终为了能在屏幕上看到像素
to being able to see pixels on our screen
现在，顶点着色器是做什么的
now, what a vertex shader does
或者说顶点着色器的代码是什么
or specifically the code that is our vertex shader
它会为我们试图渲染的每个顶点调用
that gets called for each vertex that we're trying to render
所以，在这个例子中，我们有一个三角形
so in this case we have a triangle
我们有三个顶点，知道吧
we have three vertices, okay
这意味着顶点着色器会被调用三次，明白吧
that means that the vertex shader will get called three times, okay
每个顶点调用一次
one for each vertex
并且顶点着色器的主要目的是告诉OpenGL
and the primary purpose of a vertex shader is to tell OpenGL
你希望这个顶点在屏幕空间的什么位置
where you want that vertex to be in your screen space
对吧，所以
right, so where
再一次简化这个，在你窗口的什么位置
again simplifying this where in your window
你的电脑上开着一个窗口
you have a window open on your computer
你在这里输入这些图形
where you're entering these graphics
你希望这个顶点在哪里，对吧
where would you like that vertex to be, right
这就是顶点着色器的主要目的，再说一下
that is what the primary purpose of a vertex shader is just, again
它里面有shader这个词
it has the word shader in it
所以有些人喜欢这样想
so some people like to think of it like
这与光源或着色器有关
that's having something to do with lighting or shaders or
不，这只是个程序, 这就是它
no, it's a program, that's all it is
这和实际的图形没有任何关系
so this doesn't even have anything to do with actual graphics
传统的图形，就像颜色等等
traditional graphics, in terms of like color or whatever
所有的顶点着色器，它们做的是
all the vertex shader, it does is
它指定了你想要的位置的方式
it specifies the way you want on the positions to be
话虽如此
now that being said
它也被用来解析数据从属性到下一阶段
it's also used to parse data kind of from attributes into the next stage
在我们的例子中，下一个阶段是片段着色器
and then also in our case, the next stage is the fragment shader
所以它也被用来做这个
so it's also used for that
因为当然
because of course
顶点着色器会把这些都包含进去
the vertex shader will actually take in all
我们在缓冲区中指定的顶点属性
the vertex attributes that we've specified in our buffer
在这种情况下，我们只有一个位置
in this case, we only have a position
这些我们指定的位置，如果我们回头看我们的代码
these positions that we specified, if we look back to our code
这种-0.5，以及所有这些东西
these kind of -0.5 and all of this actual this stuff
我们可以在实际的顶点着色器中访问这个
we can access this in our actual vertex shader
因为我们已经把它们指定为顶点属性指针
because we've actually specified them as vertex attribute pointers
并且你会注意到我们也把索引写为0
and you would have noticed that we also wrote the index zero
而这个索引0实际上对应于索引0
and this index zero is actually going to correspond to an index zero
在我们实际的顶点着色器中定义的那个
which will define in our actual vertex shader
并且通过这种形式
and through that kind of format
我们将能够实际访问数据
we'll be able to actually access the data
或者访问这个特定的顶点属性数据
or access this specific vertex attribute data
这个特定的顶点属性就是位置
this specific vertex attribute being the position
所以一旦我们在顶点着色器中访问了那个位置
so once we've accessed that position in our vertex shader
我们基本上就可以告诉OpenGL
we can basically tell OpenGL
我想让你把这个顶点定位到属性中指定的位置
I want you to position this vertex at the position that we're specified in the attribute
现在你可能会认为这是一个非常非常琐碎的工作
now you might be thinking this is a very very trivial task
比如为什么要存在这个
like why does this even need to exist
显然，我们想确定三角形的位置或者说是顶点的位置
obviously we want to position our triangle or our vertex position
我们在缓冲区中具体指定的位置
where we've actually specified in our buffer
是的，但是想想看，如果你有一台相机
well, yes, but think about this what if you have a camera
你在三维世界里有一个摄像机
you have a camera in a 3D world and
这是定位在某个地方
it's positioned somewhere
突然
suddenly
这些我们为三角形指定的顶点位置
these vertex positions that we've specified for our triangle
不会直接转换到屏幕上相同的位置
aren't really going to translate directly to being on the screen at those same positions
因为如果相机移动了，那么
because if the cameras moved, then
三角形也应该会移动
well, the triangle should move as well
三角形的这种转换需要在某个地方发生
and that kind of transformation of that triangle needs to happen somewhere
现在归结到某些事情上
now this comes down to certain things
在CPU和GPU上，哪个做得更快
being faster to do on the CPU and the GPU
并且关于这个有很多想法
and there's a lot of thought that goes into this
当我们开始写相机之类的东西时，我们肯定会讲到它
and we'll certainly cover it when we get up to writing cameras and stuff like that
但我说的一切
but all I'm saying is that
别去想它
don't think of it
其实并不是那么简单，我只是说
it's not actually that trivial, is just saying that
我的缓冲区中的数据
the data that is in my buffer
这就是我想要的顶点所在的位置
that is where I want my vertices is to be
因为确实有一些转换需要发生
because there are certain transformations that actually need to happen
基于某些的状态和很多其他的东西
based on certain states and just a lot of other stuff as well
但是再说一次
but again
顶点着色器的主要目的是提供那些顶点位置
the primary purpose of a vertex shader is to provide those vertex positions
如果有必要，我们需要能够提供一些转换
we need to be able to provide some kind of transformation, if necessary
以便OpenGL能把这些数字转换成屏幕坐标
so that OpenGL can actually transform these numbers into actual on screen coordinates
这样我们就能在窗口中看到我们的图形
so that we see our graphics in our window
在对的位置，在对的地方
at the right location, in the right place
所以一旦顶点着色器运行
so once the vertex shader has run
并且我记得它对每个顶点运行一次
and I remember it runs for each vertex once that's happened
那么在我们这个例子中，就会运行它三次
and we've run it in our case three times
它被调用了三次，每个顶点一次
it gets called three times, one for each vertex
我们进入了管道的下一个阶段
we move on to the next stage in our pipeline
在这个应用程序的管道中
in our pipeline for this application
下一个阶段就是片段着色器或者像素着色器
which is the fragment shader or the pixel shader
现在，片段和像素在术语上有点小差别
now fragmented fragments and pixels are a little bit different kind of terminology
我们现在不讨论这个
we're not going to get into that now
但现在你可以把像素当成片段
but for now you can kind of think of pixels as fragment
或者你可以把片段想象成像素
or rather you can think of fragments as pixels
因为片段着色器会为每个需要光栅化的像素运行一次
because the fragment shader is going to run once for each pixel that needs to get rasterized
我所说的光栅化实际上是画在屏幕上的
what I mean by rasterized is actually drawn on our screen
所以，我们的窗口基本上是由像素组成的，对吧
so our window is just basically made up of pixels, right
它就像一个像素数组
it's like a pixel array
需要发生的是我们指定的那三个顶点组成我们的三角形
what needs to happen is those three vertices that we've kind of specified that make up our triangle
现在需要用实际的像素填充
now need to get filled in with actual pixels
这就是光栅化阶段所做的
that's what the rasterization stage is doing
并且片段着色器或像素着色器
and the fragment shader or the pixel shader
就是对三角形中需要填充的每个像素调用一次
is going to get called one once for each pixel in our triangle that needs to get filled in
并且我们片段着色器或像素着色器的主要目的是决定
and the primary purpose of our fragment shader or our pixel shader is to actually decide
这个像素应该是什么颜色
which color that pixel is supposed to be
这就是它的作用，它决定了颜色
that's all it does, it just, it determines a color
像素的输出颜色，这样我们就可以得到
an output color for our pixel, so that we can get
这样像素就可以用正确的颜色着色
so that the pixel can get shaded with the right color
把它想象成一本涂色本
think of this as like a coloring book
当你只有东西的轮廓时
when you've kind of got an outline of things
但实际上，你需要给它上色
but you need to actually color it in
你需要给它涂上某种颜色
you need to shade it in with a certain color
这就是片段着色器的职责
that's what the fragment shader is responsible for
现在马上
now straight away
你可能已经注意到两者之间的区别了
you might have noticed a difference between the two
首先，像素着色器被调用三次
first, pixel shader gets called three times
片段着色器可能会被调用数万次，对吧，取决于
fragment shader might get called tens of thousands of times, right, depending on
我们的三角形在屏幕上占据了多少空间
how much room our actual triangle occupies on our screen
如果你的窗口有一个很小的三角形，一个非常小的三角形
if you have a tiny triangle, a really small triangle in your window
这可能只会被调用比如
that might only get called like
大概有50次吧
and there are 50 times or something
也许它最终会变成50像素
maybe if it ends up taking on 50 pixels
如果你有一个巨大的三角形，填满了你的窗口
if you have a giant triangle, just filling your window
你知道OpenGL之类的
you know OpenGL or something like that
它可能会占用，比如
you might it might be taking up like
我不知道，100万或者50万像素之类的
I don't know, 1 million pixels or 500,000 pixels or something like that
这意味着片段着色器实际上会被调用
which means that that fragment shader is actually going to get called
50万次
500,000 times
紧接着，我希望你们从一开始就意识到这一点
immediately and I want you guys to realize this even from the very beginning
如果我做25次某些事
that if I do something like five times five equal
我计算5*5
I calculate what five times five is
在顶点着色器中
in the vertex shader
就是25
and the value of that is 25
这个计算会发生三次
that calculation is going to happen three times
在绘制这个三角形的过程中
in the process of rendering this triangle
因为顶点着色器会被调用三次
because the vertex shader gets called three times
如果我们有一个巨大的三角形，我们在片段着色器中做5乘以5的计算
if we have a huge triangle, and we do five times five that calculation in the fragment shader
那么那个片段着色器就会被调用50万次
and that fragment shader gets called 500,000 times
瞬间，我们做了50万次乘法而不是三次
suddenly, we're doing 500,000 multiplications and not three
这里有点不同，对吧
it's a bit of a difference here, right
这就是为什么说到
which is why when it comes to
当需要优化和考虑性能时
when it comes time to kind of optimize and think about performance
这真的是所有的时间
which is really all the time
你可能已经注意到了，嘿
you can probably start to notice that, hey
在顶点着色器中做一些关键操作可能是值得的
it might be worth me doing some of these critical operations in the vertex shader
而不是在片段着色器
rather than the fragment shader
你也可以把数据从顶点着色器传递到片段着色器
and again you can pass data from the vertex shader to the fragment shader as well
所以，是的，这是值得思考的
so, yeah, just something to think about
只是想提一下
just wanted to mention that
记住那件事
keep that in mind
片段着色器
fragment shader
片段着色器里面的东西代价要高得多
things in there tend to be a lot more expensive
因为片段着色器会为每个像素运行
because, that fragment shader is going to run for each pixel
话虽这么说
that being said
有些东西显然需要按像素计算
some things obviously need to get calculated per pixel
这是个很好的例子
so a great example
我喜欢用片段着色器来举这个例子
I love bringing up this example with fragment shader
特别是光源
specifically is lighting
对吧，如果你在计算光源
right, if you're calculating lighting
每个像素都有一个颜色值，这个值是由很多东西决定的
each pixel is going to have a color value that is determined by a number of things
例如，光源，环境
for example, the lighting, the environment potentially
纹理
the texture
提供给表面的材质
the material, that's supplied to the surface
所有这些东西，对吧
all of this stuff, right
一起来确定一个特定像素的正确颜色
comes together to determine what the correct color is for a specific pixel
显然，这取决于一些输入
obviously this is going to depend on a number of inputs
例如，相机的位置在哪里
such as, where the camera position is
正如我所说的
and as I said
所有的表面属性
all the surface properties
环境属性
the environment properties
我们所有的东西都会聚集在一起
all of our stuff is going to come together
但在一天结束时
but in the end of the day
在一天结束的时候，你在片段着色器中所有的决定
at the end of the day, all you're determining in the fragment shader
是单个像素的颜色
is the color of a single pixel
这就是片段着色器的作用
that is what the fragment does
它是一个程序，运行来确定这个像素应该是什么颜色
it's a program that runs to determine which color this pixel should be
就是这样，一旦发生
that's it, once that happens
一旦片段着色器得到计算结果
once that fragment shader gets calculated
你的颜色基本上会出现在屏幕上，对吧
your color will basically make it to the screen, okay
到实际的
to the actual
到你计算机上打开的实际窗口
to your actual window that is open on your computer
我们会看到一个真正的三角形
and we'll see an actual triangle
这里是白色三角形
white triangle, in this case
因为
because
这个例子中的默认着色器在我们的驱动程序
the default shader in this example in our example in our driver
似乎默认是白色的
seems to be just defaulting to white
这可能是合适的默认着色器
which is probably the reasonable default
不管怎样，当我们开始写这些着色器的时候
but anyway, when we start writing these shaders
它将是我们指定的任何颜色
it will be whatever color we specify
所以，作为一个简单的测试，我们可以说，嘿
so, as an easy test, we could just say that, hey
这个三角形的每个像素都应该是红色的
every single pixel for this triangle should be red
我们会看到一个完全红色的三角形
and we should just see a completely red triangle
明白吧，为每个像素运行片段着色器
okay, fragment shaders run for each pixel
并且它们决定了颜色输出
and they determine the color output
顶点着色器为每个顶点运行
vertex shaders run for each vertex
它们决定了屏幕上的位置
and they determine the position on our screen
这基本上就是着色器的工作原理
that is basically how shaders work
现在，你可能认为我真的把事情过度简单化了
now, you may think that I'm really over simplifying things
因为我散发了实际管道的许多阶段
because I am emitting a lot of the stages of the actual pipeline
以及我们还有很多其他可用的着色器
and a lot of other shaders that we actually have available to us
但我不认为我真的太过简化了
but I don't think I'm actually over simplifying at all
这其实很简单
that is actually as simple as it is
话虽这么说
that being said
你可以用它做一些很酷的东西，对吧
you can do some really cool stuff with this, right
有为每个顶点运行和刷新像素的一些东西
you have something that runs for each vertex and fresh pixel
有了它，你可以完成90%的图形编程
with that, you can do like 90% of graphics programming
你在游戏中看到的一切
everything you see in games
现在大概有80%到90%是在这些着色器中完成的
nowadays is probably done 80 to 90% in those shaders
好吧，相信我
okay, and believe me
一旦你得到一些非常好看的图形
once you get to some really nice looking graphics
这些着色器可能需要数千行代码
those shaders could be thousands of lines of code
所以它们肯定会变得非常复杂
so they definitely get very complicated
更不用说那个了. 许多游戏引擎
not to mention that. a lot of the game engines
当然，每一种严格的大型游戏引擎
and certainly, every kind of serious big game engine
实际上生成着色器在飞速增加
actually generates shaders on the fly
基于你的游戏中所发生的一切
based on what's going on in your game
并且基于你所选择的图形设置
and based on what graphics settings you've selected
所有这些东西
and all of that stuff
所以有实时的着色器生成和编译是非常
so having like live shader generation and compilation is very
在游戏引擎中很常见
very common in game engines
所以确实有很多
so there's definitely a lot of really
你可以用着色器做许多很酷的事情
cool things you can actually end up doing with shaders
总之，这是对着色器的一个平缓的介绍
anyway, that's a gentle introduction to shaders
这次我们没有写任何代码
we didn't get to writing any code this time
但我们下次一定会写的
but we definitely will next time
我只是想给你们一个基本的概述
I just wanted to give you guys a basic overview
最后是一些技术概述
finally, kind of a bit of a technical overview
着色器是什么
of what shaders are
它们是如何工作的
how they work
它们用来做什么的之类的
what they used for and all that
希望我们能在下一集中看到它们的实践
and hopefully we'll see them in practice in the next episode
还有一件事我想说的是
one more thing I want to mention is that like
OpenGL着色器中的其他一切都是基于状态机工作的
everything else in OpenGL shaders work based on the state machine
这意味着
which means that
当你想要启用一个着色器
when you want to enable a shader
你要画一个三角形
you're about to draw a triangle
你想让它用一个特定的着色器来画那个三角形
and you want it to use a certain shader to draw that triangle
你启用那个着色器
you enable that shader
你也可以发送一些数据到着色器
you might also send some data to the shader
就像我们从CPU发送这个顶点数据一样
so much like we're sending this vertex data from the CPU
以顶点缓冲区的形式发送给GPU
to the GPU in the form of a vertex buffer
我们也可以通过uniform的形式发送数据到我们的着色器
we can also send data to our shader in the form of something called a uniform
这也来自CPU
and that comes from the CPU as well
所以我们设置了所有的状态，启用着色器
so we kind of set up all of that state, enable the shader
然后画出三角形
and then we draw our triangle
这也是它在OpenGL中的工作方式
that's how it works in OpenGL again
和OpenGL的其他部分一样
like the rest of OpenGL
它基本上就是一个状态机
it's pretty much just a state machine
如果你们喜欢这个视频
if you guys enjoyed this video
你可以点那个点赞按钮
you can hit that like button
你也可以访问patreon.com/TheCherno来帮助支持本系列
you can also help support this series by going over to patreon.com/TheCherno
它确实帮助我更快地制作出更多这样的
it really does help me make more of these episodes and more quickly
还有那些有趣的东西
and all that fun stuff
你也会得到一些很酷的奖励
you also get some pretty cool rewards
比如访问所有这些视频的所有源代码
such as access to all of the source code for all of these videos
一集接一集的在github上
kind of episode by episode by episode on github
以及还有很多其他的奖励
and plenty of other rewards as well
看看这个链接吧
just check out that link
如果你想进一步讨论这一集
if you want to discuss this episode further
在我的discord，有一个OpenGL频道
I've got an OpenGL channel on my discord
你可以登陆thecherno.com/discord加入这个discord
you can head on over and join that discord by going to thecherno.com/discord
它基本上就是一个不错的社区
it's basically just a nice community of people
你可以谈论c++ OpenGL游戏之类的有趣的东西
where you can talk about c++ OpenGL games all that kind of fun stuff
所以一定要加入，链接就在这儿
so definitely join that link there
下次见，再见
I will see you guys next time, goodbye